A Guide to the Papers of the Jones Family of Louisa County, Va., 1853-1908
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Civil War letters from the Jones brothers 1861-1863
  - Letters, 1861 August 9-November 29, 15 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
    "We had the reinforcements Tuesday night & Wednesday morning, part of the Washington artillery was there. There was right much of a skirmish Wednes [Wednesday] morning between Munsons Hill & Bailey's Xroads, a rifled cannon was fired at them at the xroads several times, we cd see them running in every direction when the ball struck. Our Co. was on picket Wednes night, we had a very hard time of it, it rained nearly the all time, we were very near the Federal pickets, cd hear them coughing on their post. We started back here Thursday morning & had a very hard time in the rain. Bro. Jno was a little complaining & Pen & I staid behind with him, we walked on slowly & didn't get to camp until late in the evening- all of us were the mudiest looking fellows you ever saw when we got in camp- Harry had us a nice supper ready when we arrived & you may depend upon it that all hands done ample justice to it. After Sunday we had nothing to eat but peaches & corn. I used to eat as many as seven ears of corn for a meal & peaches in ______, I wd not like to say how many Pen [had]. We had a terrible time after our blankets were sent back, we slept like hogs, piled up together on the ground about four deep. It is the greatest wonder in the world that some of us were not made sick, I don't believe a single one even took cold, & all of us are ready for another bush fight, though we wd prefer to have it in open field. My sheet is filled so I must quit. My best love to all of the dear ones at home, Aunt Cynthia's & all of my friends & accept a large share for yrself. We will write again soon. Yr devoted & most aff son P.E. Jones"
    Edloe also wrote to his mother about the fight, "My dear Ma, As I c'd not get my letter off yesterday I will write a little more to you this morning just to let you know what I've been doing since my return to camp. We were excused from all drills Friday as we were so much fatigued. We were reviewed Friday evening by Gen. [James A.] Longstreet & staff & Gen Elzy [Arnold Elzy Jones]."
    "Perhaps I ought not to tell tales out of school, but can hardly help speaking of old Elzy, he was so drunk on review that he c'd hardly sit on his horse & just before he got to the ground I saw him have a tremendous fall from his horse; he gets drunk nearly every day now, I wish we c'd get rid of him. We had inspection yesterday & Battalion drill & dress parade in the evening; a letter to Col. Hill, was read on dress parade from Col. Stuart complimenting us very much for our conduct at Munson''s Hill. We heard yesterday that they had been skirmishing near Munson's ever since we left. There seems to be a general movement with the troops now, they've moved up higher from about Centreville, Fairfax CH & all around here. I wdn't be surprised at our moving at any time, but we w'd not move very far I know..."
    Edloe wrote again to his mother "My dear Ma, I don't feel very much like writing this evening but will try to write a short letter at least. Pen gave all of you a full account of our last trip to Munson's Hill in his letter to Lute, so I will not have much news to give. We had a right rough time of it the first few days & night, but had a pleasant time the balance of the week. We had to whip the yankees out of Sewensville the first day & then go right on picket that night in the rain; you never saw such a mad set of fellows in your life as we were the night we went on picket in the rain; we could have almost skined old Major. He certainly treated us very badly & I hope we may never go under his command again. We were all delighted when Col. [James] Walker took charge of us. He has gotten well though looks right badly yet."
    "It is really amusing to hear our pickets talking with the yankee pickets. Our nearest pickets would say Bull Run to the Yankees, which made them very mad & they would always shoot at our boys whenever they would say Bull Run or cheer for Davis. The yankee pickets are in sight of our line, but not near enough to be damaged much by our balls, & they have breastworks at every post & don't show themselves much. The evening we left, David Magruder was badly wounded; he with some others were trying to creep upon some Yankees who were on post when he was shot; it was a very foolish & dangerous thing & it is a wonder, more of them were not shot. I am afraid Davy's wound will prove fatal. His father came here last night. He went to Falls Church this morning to see him. I never intend to creep upon a yankee on his post, (unless I am ordered) because nothing can be gained by it & it is very dangerous & then I don't think it is exactly right..."
    "I don't think we will have to go to Munson's anymore directly, for Uncle Phil Ashby told me that his (Longstreet's) Brigade w'd move near Munson's to remain permanently. Gen.[Joseph] Johnston has his headquarters right near us, he is only a mile on the road to Fairfax CH. Two or three regts. have moved near us in the last week. Fairfax Station has become a very busy place, another depot & two bakeries have been put recently. I don't think they have commenced using the latter yet... We expect to be reviewed this evening, if the weather don't prevent by Gen. Johnston. Generals J. Johnston & Longstreet have both complimented our Regiment very highly for the service rendered at Sewinsville, Their compliments to us will be published & I reckon Bro. John has written a piece for the Dispatch, giving an account of our trip, it will be out in a few days. I suppose you have seen the Federal account of the fight. We've heard something about a fight between Floyd & Rosencrantz, but do not know whether it is true or not...Our compliments were read out yesterday on dress parade, we are all getting proud of our Regt., call it the 'Bloody 13th'..." (Camp Blair)
    John also wrote to his mother on Sept. 20, 1861 about the fight, "As Pen and Ed have both written long accounts of our last trip down there (Munson Hill) I will refer you to yesterday's Dispatch to what 'Justice' has to say. Our Regt. was certainly most providentially preserved in the face of a greatly superior force of the enemy and having heavy skirmishes nearly all of the time we had not a man touched until just before we left when David Magruder was wounded by a very rash attempt to cut off some of the yankee picquets." He also mentioned that he is used to discomforts and advised her to not worry. He wrote that he has been hoping to receive his commission as Chaplain of the Regt. "I have been expecting every mail to bring me my commission as chaplain of the Regt. but have thus far been disappointed. I suppose that the Sec. of War has been very much pressed for time but [I] have no doubt of eventually getting the place." (Fairfax Station)
    On September 29, 1861, from Camp Blair, Edloe wrote to his father that Colonel Stuart has been made Brigadier General. He added, "I think he ought to thank the 13th for his promotion."
  - Letters, 1862 Mar.16-October 23, 6 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Letters include a letter from Pendleton to his mother on June 12, 1862. He wrote in detail about the war, "Jackson is the greatest General of the Age & his brilliant achievements with a hand full of men badly equipped and poorly fed and clothed carry us back to the chivalric days of yore when men fought for Liberty and Home and remind us forcibly of the warrior Napoleon. But I must resume my sketch of our maneuvers & transactions which must be meager & imperfect. On Monday the 26th, [May 1862] we followed up the enemy hotly & our cavalry chased them from Martinsburg. This was their General Receiving Depot for this Dept. of their Army and the stores captured were of innumerable variety and of exceeding great value to the needy Rebels- such as salt, leather, coffee, [ordinance], clothing & _____."
    "Next day our Brigade moved to this side of Winchester and the weary worn soldiers congratulated themselves upon the apparent prospects of rest and quiet; we remained here however only one night and next evening we were pitching tents while the rain pound down as marching orders were received. 'Twas with no reluctance, however, that the men prepared to follow the gallant 'Stonewall' and marched through the hardest rain & deep mud fifteen miles after dark in the direction of Charlestown."
    "Wednesday the 28th [May 1862] we reached Charlestown early in the day and met with unbounded & enthusiastic welcome from the citizens. The Federals fled before us and stores fell into our hands and many prisoners. We had camped in a lovely spot and somewhat rested when there was an alarm and our regiment went off at 'doublequick' in direction of Harper's Ferry, eight miles distant. Our regiment was delighted at the idea of once more visiting the spot where they spent their military childhood; we got in sight of the surrounding hills, and a few cannon shots were exchanged between the belligerents and nothing more; no damage to either party, I suppose. We occupied our same encampment and early next morning were again called out & our cavalry pursued the enemy into poor [Maryland]. But all at once orders were received to march back; the rain poured down in timult. The roads were already heavy with mud, our Brigade marched twenty six miles through all this & camped near Winchester- it rained hard all night long and the men were poorly fed if indeed they had anything that night."
    "I can remember nothing of special interest to you from that day until Sunday (1st June), [1862 Battle of Seven Pines] the great battle day of ancient & modern days; yet the hardships, heavy rains and fast days made a lasting impression upon me and if we mounted individuals suffered you can imagine how men on foot fared. The cause of the retreat as you are doubtless aware was the design of the Federals to entrap and overwhelm Jackson with numbers; [General James] Shields with a large column advanced towards Swift Run Gap from Manassas and [General John Charles "Pathfinder"] Freemont came down on the left from Romney while [General Nathaniel Prentiss] Banks reinforcements were to meet him in front. But Jackson can never be caught & with his usual skill he has extricated himself from this trap while the enemy has been completely baffled. Sunday 1st inst.[June 1862] he engaged Fremont near Strasburg routed him with a small force; he continued his retreat while the men were worn out completely & his army showed great signs of demoralization."
    "For one week more, we moved back slowly while the cavalry kept up daily engagements with the cautiously pursuing enemy. Saturday 7th inst. [June 1862] in the afternoon we had a considerable cavalry engagement near Harrisonburg killing and capturing many of the enemy & putting them to flights; yet in this victory when he was about to commence a carier of fame unequalled by anything heretofore recorded on [historic page fill the brave chivalric], daring, generous Ashby [Turner Ashby]- a man who has beside all others been able to [inlain] most confidence in his own troops & greatest [tremor] among the enemy he so much hated; his splendid horse had just been shot from under him & he was gallantly leading on foot a brave band of infantry where a bullet pierced his heart and horse and rider lay breathless upon the same bloody battle fields."
    " Sunday (8th) [June 1862] early Jackson engaged Shields who had possession of Port Republic & the bridge and dislodged him and about midday (General Richard Stoddert) Ewell's Divisions met and successfully routed Fremont's column; this was across the river from Port Republic which you see would make Shields in Ewell's rear while Jackson was upon road D of my rough map. The thirteenth was in the [thickest] of the fight and suffered some; it behaved most gallantly- the Blues were not with the regiment but detailed to support Capt. Courtney's Battery which guarded another position of the field and was not in action. On Monday next day (9th) [June 1862 Battle of Port Republic] we crossed the river early and burnt the bridge (F) then attacked Shields on road E and routed him; captured many prisoners; killed many and took a battery; the casualties on our side were heavy but I do not know to which extent. In the evening as we pursued Shields on E toward Gap A and were capturing many prisoners, Fremont leaving again [rallied approached] from Harrisonburg & appeared with large forces in front of Port Republic; he could not cross and busied himself with shilling our Hospitals & Ambulance train of which I was an eyewitness. We retreat[ed] to the mountain hollow by road G and remained there from Monday night until Wednesday when we started back by road H.
    On September 23, 1862 Edloe wrote a letter from Winchester about his mother's death. She had been caring for Edloe who was seriously injured in battle [shot in the lungs] and bedridden at home in Louisa. He does not recover from this wound and dies in February 1863. His mother passed away while caring for him. He wrote, "And our dear mother is no more! Absent from the loved scenes of home and mingling constantly with the rough society and wicked association of the camp I could scarcely realize the sad and mournful occurrence [that] my mother, she who had raised me, and protected & defended me through life's most trying and dangerous hours, had been taken away from us! I can only realize now how fortunate I have been through life in having such a tender adviser & counselor, one contains such characteristics as we can only express in three words- a tender, virtuous, Christian mother!..."
    On September 29, 1862 Pendleton wrote to his sister Lute, "Our division is encamped near Bunker's Hill fourteen miles from Winchester and everything seems to indicate quiet and rest after the stormy scenes through which we have passed since we left the Rapid Ann. [Rapidan River] The army is completely demoralized and worn out... Uncle John [William Jones] is with Early [General Jubal Anderson Early] now who commands our division and I see him quite frequently- he looks well but is tired of this duty & told me he was going to apply to General [Robert E.] Lee for some other duty. It is reported by rumors that General (George ) Pickett is to be assigned to the command of Ewell's Division. There has been great talk this week of peace and many firmly believed that ninety day armistice was about to be again between the National authorities. All hands are getting sick and tired of this wicked and unhallowed war. The Yankees themselves not withstanding their boasted preparations and abilities to conquer us speedily are also wearied with war and if we could only carry the war into their own territory they would soon be in favor of amicable adjustments." (Folder 4, Sept. 29, 1862 Pendleton to his sister, Lute. (Near Bunker's Hill)
    On October 23, 1862 Pendleton wrote to his sister Helen from Bunker's Hill near Martinsburg that "Jackson's corps has since been engaged in destroying the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad in this vicinity; today they are at work between Martinsburg and Harper's Ferry and there are some prospects of a fight with the enemy as we draw nearer Harper's Ferry; but most of [General George B.] McClellan's Army seems to have disappeared since the news from Kentucky save some forces at the Ferry to marauding parties of cavalry here & there. The news from [General Braxton] Bragg's army is encouraging if true and the fact of a brilliant success seems well established & credible although we have exaggerated details. Stuart's raid into Pennsylvania has eclipsed any dash or daring since the war begun; he brought away valuable property but the destruction of so many arms & so much ordnance & the moral effect are the greatest objects gained. Every one thought it a precursor of some grand move of the whole army but I believe that opinion has exploded and all believe that the army will fall back [soon dishonor] in a few days; in fact Longstreet corps has already moved & encamped near Winchester. Soldiers all wish the war to close & of consequence there are thousands of rumors afloat about peace. But I see no signs of peace while both parties are endeavoring to put forth all their strength & are making renewed effort to annihilate each other. If whipped the North is no longer the nation it once was- poverty will reign where wealth was universal; if subjugated, the prosperity, happiness and being of the South forever perish, so that it is a question of life or death with both parties; of course there we must expect a protracted struggle when such momentous consequences are involved in the issue, when the resources of each party are so great, to when the combatants are stubborn Americans! Something may end the war sooner than I expect but I see no sign of speedy termination now."
  - Letters, 1863 January 2-April 5, 4 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
    On January 2, 1863 the Reverend John William Jones (from camp near Fort Royal) wrote to his wife on about religion and the war, "Just returned from preaching for my namesake [Uncle John William Jones] at 25th Virginia. I tried to make ___ practical talk on the blessing wh. the Lord has given us during the past year as a Nation, a brigade, and as individuals and to draw thence lessons of thankfulness for the past and trustfulness and obedience for the future. I tried to preach to myself as well as to others for truly the Lord has been good to me during the past years- far more than I have in any way deserved. I enter the New Year with deep humiliation in view of my shortcomings in the past (both in what I have done and what I have failed to do) and with many resolves for the future- God help me to keep them. Let us begin the New Year with determination to help each other make progress in personal holiness and labor together for the good of others. If our hearts are only kept right it is always easy and pleasant to do good e.g. I have generally found it very hard to talk with officers (especially complete strangers) on the subject of religion and yet when an occasion offered this evening I found it easy and very pleasant to talk to Col. Higinbottom (of the 25th) about his soul, and urge him to seek after a personal interest in the savior's blood." John also mentioned that he is glad to hear that General Lee has somewhat relaxed the rigor of his orders about furloughs.
    On January 4, 1863 (Early's Brigade) Pendleton wrote to his sister Lute, "Politics visit the haunts of the camp and field and now there are lively discussions as to who will be the nest Governor [of Virginia] and who is to succeed the lamented Preston? in Congress. William (Extra-Billy) Smith who is Colonel of the 49th Va. (in our Brigade) is highly commended for the Post of Governor and could our boys decide the elections his chances would be favorable."
    On February 26, 1863 (near Fredericksburg) Pendleton wrote to his father about the death of his brother Edloe and elaborates about his great character and how sadly he will be missed.
    On April 5, 1863 (near Rappahanock) Pendleton wrote to his father about his strong feelings toward General [Extra Billy William] Smith and Colonel [James] Walker. "General Early announced his permanent staff to the Division yesterday...We expect General Smith to assume command of the Brigade one day this week and the entire command are regretting deeply that the Services of Col. Walker will be lost. That veteran soldier and gallant officer is now absent on three weeks leave of absence and in the meanwhile speaks confidently of resigning his commission; he bade us all farewell and said he did not expect to return again. This appointment of Gen. Smith is the most outrageous political trick that any times ever afforded. Col. Walker has the highest recommendation for promotion ever given by Ewell, Jackson and Lee, and every officer- save two or three Smith's in Col. Smith's old regiment- 49th Va.- petitioned for Col. W. to be assigned to this Brigade which he has commanded for seven months. I hope old Bill will be defeated for Governor."
  - Letters n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Included with several undated letters is one that Edloe wrote to his mother, "... I like this place first rate, would not care how long we would remain here. I had become right much attached to Harper's Ferry and hated to leave right bad. I reckon Pen wrote the particulars about the fight, so I won't say anything about it. I am afraid we won't get in shooting distance of the Yankees at all. They are such cowards. You must excuse this short note. Don't be uneasy about us, we are very well & ready to take another march if necessary. My best love to all. yr devoted & most aff son." This letter was probably written in 1861 and showed that Edloe loved soldier life and reveled in the comraderie, discipline and strenuous physical demands of camp.
- Series II: Other Jones family papers 1853-1860; 1865-1907
  - Genealogy n.d. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Letter and notes describing the Jones family genealogy
  - R. T. Hanks to sister Page Tucker n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Jones relatives (descendants)
  - E.M. Harris to the Reverend John William Jones n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Mother of a soldier wrote to the Reverend John William Jones asking him if he knew anything about her son's dying moments
  - Thomas Hume, Jr. to the Reverend John William Jones n.d.; 1859-1860 (Box-folder 1:10)
    Includes six letters about his church related activities; invitations to visit each other; status of his health; and words of friendship.
    One of the letters from Thomas Hume, Jr. to the Reverend John William Jones was written August 2, 1860 and described an outing with some of his lady friends. He was taken with one of the ladies and wrote about her and the art of flirtation that she exhibited.
  - Ann Pendleton Jones to her son the Reverend John William Jones 1856-1859 (Box-folder 1:11)
    Includes twenty-seven letters about family and neighborhood news.
  - Edloe Jones to his brother the Reverend John William Jones 1860 (Box-folder 1:12)
    On January 14, 1860 Edloe wrote to his brother John about his studies. He wrote that Latin doesn't agree with him, and he described an adventure catching an opossum that was a good size to eat. He also inquired about John's love life. He wrote, "Do you intend on getting a wife out there?"... "I think Miss. Daisy would suit you very well, don't know whether you could get her or not." He also wrote, "Pa got a letter from Pen a few days before he went to University, whenever he wants a little money he writes Pa a nice letter."
  - Francis William Jones to his son the Reverend John William Jones 1855 Oct. 16-Sept.10; 1859; 1865 Nov.1-13 (Box-folder 1:13)
    Twenty one letters including one dated June 3,1859 when his father,Francis William Jones wrote to his son John about a position being offered by Dr. McGuffey.
    Another letter from his father was written on October 16, 1855 where he wrote to John expressing his support of his chosen career in theology: "I have no objection to the place you have marked out for yourself. I need not assure you that I have given the subject my most prayerful consideration & I do not know what better you can do. You can fully appreciate the feelings I have when I think of the many loved ones I have to provide for with no means to do so as I desire but is all right. God will take care of those who trust in him as they ought to."
  - Mary Helen Jones Sumner to her brother the Reverend John William Jones 1854-1856; n.d. (Box-folder 1:14)